"3D Monster Maze"

Can you find your way through the Maze? The EXIT is there
somewhere, but then so is a T.REX and its after you. All in 3D
you've never seen anything like this before!

An introduction is provided, in the program, which includes
instructions.

All key presses are single keys (ie. press C for CONT, etc.).

The curser keys move you in the direction indicated on the keys
and auto-repeat.

ie: 5..... Turn LEFT: 8 Turn RIGHT; 7 Move FORWARD.

If you wish to turn round completely, turn to the Left, or
Right twice.

After a short period, during which a random maze is developed,
you will be within the maze of TYRANNOSAURUS REX.
You will see grey walled corridors disappearing off to your left
and/or right. The black walls are those of the corridor down
which you are passing. Those walls and corridors directly to
either side of you can be seen at the edge of the display. If you
are looking directly at a wall in front of you, it is grey.

TACTICAL HINTS

Use the information provided to estimate the whereabouts of
TeREX. If you are told to RUN, do just that, since you can
outrun him. When REX lies in wait, spend the time learning the
maze and trying to find the EXIT. But beware he could be
around that corner!

The EXIT is always at the end of a cul-de-sac.

GENERAL NOTES

Do not delete or alter any statement, since the program is not
relocatable.

Line 370 forms part of a wait loop, initially set at 5, You may
change this, in the range 0 to 9 to make the game go faster or
slower.

LOADING time approximately 4 minutes.

COPYRIGHT 1982 NEW GENERATION SOFTWARE
No unauthorised copying or hiring Of the program/tape ais per-
mitted.

Cover artwork by Rob Pengilley, Bath.

