Cubix

Development: Gogin
Country: Russia
Memory: 128K

The first 3D platformer of its kind for the 
ZX Spectrum! The game takes place in the 
distant geometric universe of the Cubes, 
where the laws of physics obey symmetry, and 
the world consists of perfect cubes. Towers 
soar into the sky, cities shimmer with bright 
facets. The heart of this world is the Sacred 
Talisman, a magical dice that radiates balance and order.

One day, a mysterious villain appeared from the 
Shadow Dimension - Hexatron, the lord of chaos. 
He hated the perfection of the Cubes and longed to 
destroy their harmony. The Hexatron stole the Sacred 
Talisman and shattered it into six separate facets. 
He hid each of them on top of the Great Towers, filled 
with traps, labyrinths, and trials.

Our protagonist Bix, a simple villager who accidentally 
escaped the curse, decides to defy fate! He must climb 
each of the towers, overcome treacherous trials, collect 
all the facets of the Talisman and restore it to restore 
peace to his people!

The genre of the game is a puzzle platformer with 
elements of metroidvania. The game has 6 large game 
locations-"towers", unlike each other; A variety of 
game mechanics (more than 10 pieces), cute enemies 
and brain-blowing logical riddles. As you progress 
through the game, the main character unlocks more and 
more new abilities that allow you to pass the "towers" 
non-linearly (that is, in different ways and routes), 
the mechanics of the puzzles change, and the complexity 
of the puzzles increases.

Controls

On the menu:
1 – start with WASD control
2 – launch with OAOP control
3 – start with arrow control

In the game:
Q, Up – jump (QAOP control or arrows)
Space – jump (WASD control)
A, Down, S – sit down
O, Left, A – to the left
P, Right, D — to the right
Space – Action (QAOP control or arrows)
Enter - Action (WASD Control)
R - Game menu

