
                    THE GAC ADVENTURE
                    WRITERS HANDBOOK

                       CONTENTS

             How to write a good Adventure    1
             What is a Condition?             4
             Markers                          7
             Counters                        11
             Diagnostics Screen              15
             Text                            16
             Graphics                        19
             Advanced Commands               20
             Advanced use of Conditions      23
             Multiple Loading Techniques     26
             Error Messages                  27
             Errata Information              28
             Amstrad Hints & Tips            30
             BBC Hints & Tips                35
             Commodore Hints & Tips          38
             Spectrum Hints & Tips           41

             Adventure Clubs & Magazines     46





             Grateful thanks to all contributors :

   Simon Lipscomb, Tim Walsha, Pat Winstanley, John Gwinnell
                       & Lesley Anderson


The Graphic Adventure  Creator  (GAC)  is  Copyright  Incentive
Software Ltd/Sean Ellis. 1985 & 1986.
All rights of the producer and of the owner of the  work  being
produced are reserved. Unauthorised copying of this work  as  a
whole or in part are strictly prohibited. The publisher assumes
no responsibility for errors. Although every effort is made  to
ensure the information in this publication is true and correct.


                   HOW TO WRITE A GOOD ADVENTURE


The best adventures all contain the following features:

1.  A well defined and interesting plot.
2.  A good atmosphere.
3.  Originality and inventiveness in the problems  -  but  with  a
    good deal of logic.
4.  A lot of responses to player input.
5.  A degree of humour.

These features are described more fully below.

1.  PLOT


Try to make your plot original,  not  just  another  "collect  the
treasures" or "rescue the princess" clone.  You  must  be  careful
that your plot will work in adventure format -  a  hijacked  plane
scenario would probably be a bit limited.
A plot should neither be too simple nor too complex as the  player
will either become too bored or too confused.
The plot can be presented on the inlay or accompanying  literature
on a loading screen or at the game start, but these methods  allow
for gradually less plot to be shown.  Plot on  the  inlay  can  be
read in the shop and may incite the  customer  to  buy  the  game.
Also any nasty pirates won't know what's going on!

2. ATMOSPHERE


Room descriptions do not have to be big to be  atmospheric.   Good
use of adjectives and adverbs usually does the trick.
For example:

GOOD: You're in a cold damp  east-west  corridor.  The  walls  are
      bathed in flickering torch light.
BAD : You're in a corridor. Torches are  on  the  walls.  East  or
      West.
Aim to  include  available  exits,  but  try  to  make  them  more
interesting than "Exits lead North, East  and  West".   "The  path
winds  it's  way  Northwards  into   the   mountains",   is   more
interesting.

3. PROBLEMS


Problems consist either of having to get  past  some  obstacle  or
interacting with other characters or objects.   A  problem  should
always have a reason for solving it, usually  to  reach  some  new
locations or to get an essential  object.   Problems  are  usually
successive, for example,  solving  one  problem,  gets  an  object
needed to solve the next.
When designing a  problem  keep  it  relevant  to  the  plot,  for
example, coping with technology/getting past robots in  a  science
fiction game.
The problem should not be so obscure as  to  make  it  impossible,
unless some clue is given elsewhere.

                                  1

The solution to  a  problem  should  be  relevant  to  the  actual
problem.  For example, if the player meets  a  vampire  they  will
assume that the way to  defeat  it  is  one  of  the  old  vampire
methods, (e.g. garlic, cross, holy water and so on). If  it  turns
out that the way past the vampire is to "REMOVE  SHOES"  then  the
player will feel cheated.

Gets Harder

Adventures should  get  harder  as  they  progress,  so  that  the
beginners get some easy  problems  to  start  them  off  and  more
experienced players will not sail straight through to the end.
Easy problems at the beginning should have plenty of clues  as  to
what the player should do and plenty of responses, (see below).
They will also give the player a feel of  your  adventure  writing
technique so they will know what to expect later on.
DON'T put any "Instant death" high  priorities  in  right  at  the
start, unless they are  for  walking  off  a  cliff  or  something
similar. In fact the player should never be killed  unless  he/she
deserves it - moving into a new location and  finding  out  it  is
quicksand will annoy the player unless it is  specifically  stated
that there is quicksand in that direction.
A player attacking a lion with bare hands is asking  for  trouble.
A player walking along a path is not.


4. RESPONSES


A game should  have  lots  relevant  responses  to  wrong  inputs,
instead of saying "You can't", it will say why you can't.
An example of this would be:

The player is on the south bank of a river in a  copse  of  trees.
The way across the river is to build a raft using the axe and  the
rope.
Error messages can be written for:

a)  Trying to cross the river without the raft -
    "Full of crocodiles", "Can't swim", etc.
b)  Building the raft without the axe -
    "You try to fell the tree using karate, but fail".
c)  Building a raft having cut down the trees, but not having the
    twine -
    "The logs don't seem to want to stay together".
d)  Finally two messages for building the raft successfully, and
    crossing the river.

5. HUMOUR


In general, humour found in adventure games is the wry comment  or
sarcasm.  Humourous responses  are  usually  those  for  when  the
player does something  wrong  or  stupid.   Total  all  out  silly
adventures and spoofs, (e.g. "Bored of The Rings"), should only be
attempted if you are above averagely witty or the player will  fed
up with the same old jokes every time.
No game should take itself too seriously, it is after all  only  a
game!



                                  2

GRAPHICS


Graphics are becoming an important part of adventures these  days,
at least  as  far  as  the  commercial  aspect  is  concerned.   A
text-only adventure written on GAC  is  only  utilising  half  the
features, but it is best to leave the graphics until last and  use
up the remaining memory rather than trying to  cram  an  adventure
into memory left after drawing the graphics.

If you try to have a graphic for every location, you will  end  up
either with a small adventure or poor graphics.  The  best  tactic
is to use various merged elements, and to  place  graphics  evenly
throughout the adventure, in that the player goes for roughly  the
same amount of time between illustrated locations.  It is best  to
draw graphics of the more interesting  places  in  your  game.   A
simple east-west tunnel in not the most inspiring of  places,  but
the 50 foot statue of the 12 armed  warrior-deity  could  make  an
impressive picture.

If you are not particularly good at drawing, you can always get  a
friend to  do  the  graphics.   Failing  that  make  the  pictures
informative rather than artistic.
Some pointers to follow as regards to graphics  are  to  keep  the
paper colour dark and pen colour light.  Choose similar colours as
opposed to wildly different ones, in the hope of getting  lots  of
shades.
As a final point, remember that most adventure reviews do not have
graphics ratings.


BELIEVABILITY


This may seem like a strange thing to ask of a  game  where  magic
works, or aliens frequently pop in for tea, but your  game  should
have an internal logic.
Believability is enhanced by relevant placement of  locations  and
objects, for example, a snowfield next to a desert, or an  ironing
board in a forest, do not help believability.
The best way to make an adventure seem realistic  is  to  ask  the
question why? of all features.  If you have no answer, change that
feature.


PLAYTESTERS


Always get someone else, (at least one other), to play your  game.
This way you will be able to find out if  your  problems  are  too
easy or too difficult, which responses to put in and any  mistakes
in spelling or syntax, (other people tend to  spot  your  mistakes
more easily!). And when your playtester gets stuck  or  stops  the
game, don't just tell them the way round it, but note things  down
and adapt your adventure to accept his  responses  and/or  put  in
more clues etc.



                                  3

                         WHAT IS A CONDITION?

In an adventure the player  has  freedom  to  type  anything  at  the
keyboard. Only a tiny minority of the possible inputs  has  relevance
to the adventure, so some method must be used to tell the interpreter
what these are and how to deal with them. The method used in  GAC  is
the use of four different types of conditions.

a) Connections
b) Local Conditions
c) Low Priority Conditions
d) High Priority Conditions

Every command that the player can type which causes some action to be
taken by the interpreter must have a condition of one type or  other,
as the conditions are what cause action to be taken. It isn't  always
necessary to have a separate  condition  for  every  single  relevant
input. Very often a group of similar commands can be lumped  together
into one 'blanket' condition which will deal with them all (e.g. GET,
DROP, EXAMINE etc). But remember..... no condition....no action!

The term condition is a little misleading as this implies only a test
for truth. In GAC  the  term  condition  is  used  to  cover  actions
too..... sometimes with no 'condition' attached.

The general construction of conditions is as follows;

IF ( whatever is inside the brackets is  all  true ) {Then, and  only
then } perform  all  the actions between the end of the brackets  and
the 'END' command.

The conditional part " IF (.....) " can be omitted altogether  if  it
is required  that  a  particular  action  be  performed  every  turn.
Normally, this type of entry would go in the High Priority section.

When the conditional part is used,  what  it  does  is  test  to  see
whether the player's input and  any  other  relevant  information  is
true. If everything in the brackets is true, all  the  actions  after
the brackets will be performed. If anything within  the  brackets  is
not true, none of the actions after the brackets will  be  performed,
so  the  condition  will  be  ignored.  The  search  through  further
conditions will continue until either a condition which  is  true  is
found and acted upon, or no true condition at all is found  in  which
case no action will be taken, and the player will  be  asked  to  try
again.

 Order of Priorities

Each condition is looked at in turn and  acted  upon  if  appropriate
until either a command to stop looking at any further  Local  or  Low
Priority conditions is found ( WAIT or OKAY at  the  end  of  a  true
condition which jumps  the  player  to  the  beginning  of  the  High
Priority conditions ), or all conditions have been  checked  and  the
player is asked for the next command. The order in  which  conditions
are checked is predetermined  and  very  important.....  Connections,
Local, Low, High.


                                 4

 CONNECTIONS .. are conditions which the writer can  adjust  only  to
the extent of which movement verb leads to which location. Any  input
by the player which matches a valid connection in the room where  the
player is will be acted upon, the player moved to  a  new  room,  The
High Priority conditions checked and acted upon if  appropriate,  and
the "What now?" message printed....WITHOUT LOOKING AT  ANY  LOCAL  OR
LOW PRIORITY CONDITIONS!!! So if you want a move  from  one  room  to
another to be conditional upon ( say ) possession of the correct key,
that particular room connection must  not  be  entered  in  the  room
description, otherwise the player will move before any check is  made
as to whether or not the key is available.  Instead,  the  connection
must be ommitted from the room description  connections  and  entered
elsewhere, usually as a LOCAL condition. For instance, say you wanted
the player to he able to move north from room 6 to  room  7  if,  and
only if a key was being carried, the entry would be as follows;.

         IF ( VERB {north} AND AVAI {key} ) GOTO 7 WAIT END

This would be entered as a Local condition for room 6, but  no  entry
would be made for 'north' in the room connections.


 LOCAL CONDITIONS ..... If no valid  connections  are  found  or  the
player has not typed a movement verb, the next set of conditions will
be searched ( in number order ) for a match with the  player's  input
and status. These will be the Local conditions relating to  the  room
where the player currently is. ( If the player is in  room  15,  only
room 15 conditions will be checked,  regardless  of  whether  another
room's local conditions match ). If and  when  a  true  condition  is
found it is acted upon, and if a 'WAIT' or 'OKAY' is  encountered  in
that condition, a jump will be made to the High Priority  conditions,
then to the player's next command as above. If no true  condition  is
found, or one is found and acted upon which has no 'WAIT'  or  'OKAY'
command in its actions, further searching continues.  Only  when  all
relevant Local conditions have been looked at are  the  Low  Priority
conditions checked.

 LOW PRIORITY .... Assuming no jump has been made, the  Low  Priority
conditions are checked for a match in exactly the  same  way  as  the
Local ones. Whereas only  the  Local  conditions  pertaining  to  the
current room  are  available  for  checking,  all  the  Low  Priority
conditions are available. Again, true conditions are looked  for  and
acted upon, and if no jump is  made,  High  Priority  conditions  are
checked.

 HIGH PRIORITY CONDITIONS ... These are always checked and acted upon
after every turn, regardless of whether any Connections, Local or Low
conditions have been performed. A  'WAIT'  or  'OKAY'  command  which
stops further checking of  Low  or  Local  conditions  jumps  to  the
beginning of the High Priority table  after  incrementing  the  turns
counter. Once The High Priority conditions have been 'done' the "What
now?" message is printed ( if the player is still in the game!).



                                  5

 Use of Conditions

CONNECTIONS
Used ONLY for unconditional moves between rooms.

LOCAL CONDITIONS
Used for actions which will only be performed in one location

LOW PRIORITY
Used for actions which can take place anywhere

HIGH PRIORITY
Used for conditions and actions to occur before  the  players  input.


 Drafting Conditions

When working out the form of a new condition, it is useful to  ignore
noun, verb, object, marker numbers, and write the logic out in  plain
English. Think of the condition as split into two parts;

1) TRUE OR FALSE....... what needs to be true for the actions  to  be
                        performed?

2) WHAT TO DO.......... what actions are  required  for  the  desired
                        effect?

e.g. IF ( VERB {hit} AND NOUN {granny} AND HERE  {granny]}  ) .......
[then] MESS 'she hits you back harder!' WAIT END

Only when the logic of the condition is clear on paper should you
insert the relevant numbers. Don't stop in the middle of a condition
to enter a new message or verb etc, as doing so will probably ruin
your train of thought. Also, keep your draft on paper until the
condition has been entered and debugged. It's a lot easier to read
and understand English than algebra!









                                 6

                               MARKERS


While writing an adventure you will come across many situations where,
depending upon the player's actions, the environment can be in one  of
two states. For instance imagine..... the following text greeting  the
player on entering a location;

      "You are in a farmhouse kitchen. You can also see a table."

Now suppose you wanted the player to examine the table, and  in  doing
so find a bottle. This is  simple  to  set  up,  merely  by  having  a
condition on the lines of;

A) IF ( VERB {examine} AND NOUN {table} ) BRIN {bottle} LOOK WAIT END

On typing "exam table" the player would be rewarded with the following
text;

 "You are in a farmhouse kitchen. You can also see a table, a bottle."

There is just one snag with this routine. If the  player  again  types
"exam table"   (which  is  perfectly  reasonable  since   occasionally
adventures provide for a sequence of objects to be found)  the  bottle
will be acted upon by the BRIN command again. Since you won't want the
player to discover the  bottle  every  time  he  examines  the  table,
something must be done to let GAC know that  the  bottle  has  already
been found.

This is where the use of a marker comes in! A marker can  be  imagined
as a switch which can be either on or  off,  but  no  other  state  is
possible. In the situation described above you would allocate a marker
to 'mark' whether or not the bottle had been discovered. If the player
types "exam table" and the marker says that the  bottle  has  not  yet
been found, GAC needs to know that it can bring the bottle. If however
the bottle has already been found, GAC  needs  to  know  that  further
examination of the table will NOT result in the bottle being  brought.
And since examining the table after the bottle has been found ought to
give some description of the table, two conditions need to be set  up,
(B) & (C);

B) IF  (  VERB  {examine}  AND  NOUN  {table}   AND  RES?  x   )  BRIN
{bottle} SET x  LOOK WAIT END

C) IF ( VERB {examine} AND NOUN {table}   AND  SET?  x   )  MESS  {see
nothing special} WAIT END

So if the bottle has not been found, condition (B) will be acted  upon
because marker x is "reset". ( All markers are reset initially  unless
you set them, except markers 0 & 1 ).

If condition (B) is acted upon, one of the things that will happen  is
the "setting" of marker x in the action part of the condition. So  if,
at a later stage,  the  player  tries  to  examine  the  table  again,
condition (B) will no longer be true. GAC, on reaching "res?  x"  will
check marker x and find that it is "set". This being so, it will  move
on to look for a true condition.... condition (C). Here GAC is told to
check for marker x being "set ?", which it is. So condition  (C)  will
be acted upon giving the message "You see nothing special".


                                 7

Once a marker is set, or reset it will remain in that state unless GAC
acts upon a condition which contains a command to  switch  it  to  the
opposite state.

There are only four possible expressions which can be  used  regarding
markers:

 SET? x  - is used in the 'IF' part of  a  condition,  ie  within  the
brackets to ask GAC to check if the marker x is "set". If marker x  is
not "set" the condition is not true, as so will not be acted upon.

 RES? x  - is also used in the 'IF' part,  to  ask  GAC  to  check  if
marker x is "reset". If marker x is not "reset",  the  condition  will
not be acted upon.

 SET x  - is used in the 'action' part of the condition ie  after  the
brackets. If marker x is reset, "set x" will change it to being "set".
If marker x is already "set" it will remain "set.

 RESE x  - is used in the 'action part. If marker x is "set", "rese x"
will change it to being "reset". If marker x  is  already  "reset"  is
will remain "reset".

So if you want a condition to include  a  check  on  the  state  of  a
marker, use RES? or SET", inside the brackets.

If you want to change the state of a marker, use SET or RESE after the
brackets.


                           LIGHT AND DARK

To indicate a light or dark room, a special  marker  is  set  aside...
marker 1.

If the player is  in  a  light  room  and  moves  into  one  you  have
designated as being dark, marker 1 is changed from being set to  being
reset. In this special case only the action words  SET  and  RESE  are
needed. The way to acheive a change of light conditions is as follows.

For this example, imagine two rooms;

                  ____________             ____________
                  |          |             |          |
                  |  ROOM 1  |             |  ROOM 2  |
                  |          |-------------|          |
                  | (LIGHT)  |             |  (DARK)  |
                  |__________|             |__________|

a) Make sure there is NO connection E 2 from Room 1, and NO connection
W 1 from Room 2, in the movement line of the room description. If  you
don't, typing the relevant direction will cause  a  move  to  be  made
without looking at any conditions.


                                  8

b) Make local conditions as follows;

ROOM 1.... IF ( VERB {east} ) RESE 1 GOTO 2 WAIT END
ROOM 2.... IF ( VERB {west} ) SET 1 GOTO 1 WAIT END

What happens is this: If you are in room 1 and type "east", GAC  looks
through the connections, doesn't find an east connection, so moves  on
to the Local Conditions for room 1. Here  it  finds  a  condition  for
moving east and acts upon it, in the process 'resetting' marker 1. Now
GAC knows ( because it is already built in) that if marker 1 is reset,
the current room is dark. The current room in  this  case  is  room  2
since the GOTO moves the player  there.  Since  marker  is  signifying
darkness, the room description is not printed. Instead the appropriate
message, "it in dark. You can't see." greets the player.

If the player is in room 2 and types "west", GAC moves the  player  to
room 1, "setting" marker 1 in the process. Now that marker 1  is  set,
GAC knows the player is in a light room and prints the description  of
room 1.

If you have dark rooms in your adventure, you will  probably  want  to
provide the player with a lamp. Again, a special marker is  set  aside
by GAC to cope with lamps... marker 2.

If the player is in a room and both marker 1 and marker 2 are "reset",
GAC will refuse to describe the room, instead giving the "It is  dark"
message. So marker 2 is used  to  tell  GAC  whether  a  lit  lamp  is
available.

There are three possibilities  for  the  circumstances  in  which  the
player may move east from room 1 to room 2:

a) Carrying a lit lamp with him.
b) The lit lamp is already in room 2 having been left there earlier.
c) The lit lamp is neither carried nor in room 2 already.

Now if either (a) or (b) is the case, GAC needs to know that light  is
available in the dark room when the player reaches  it,  ie  marker  2
must be "set" when the player gets there. This is  achieved  with  the
following line:

Room 1: Line 1:

IF ( 2 IN {lit lamp} OR CARR {lit lamp} AND VERB {east} ) RESE 1 SET 2
GOTO 2 WAIT END

This line tells GAC that if the lamp is in room 2  or  the  player  is
carrying it and east is typed, rese marker 1 to say the room is  dark,
and set marker 2 to say there is a  light  source  available....  then
move to room 2 .

If neither of the above are true, ie the lit lamp is not in room 2 and
the player is not carrying it, when east  is  typed  in  room  1,  the
condition will be ignored. But we still want the player to be able  to
get to room 2, even though he will get a "It's dark" message,  so  the
following line must be inserted after the first:



                                  9

Room 1: Line 2:

IF ( VERB {east} ) RESE 1 RESE 2 GOTO 11 WAIT END

This line will take care of possibility (c)

When setting up the  "light  lamp"  command,  ignore  the  setting  of
markers and let the local movement conditions take care of it.  Simply
by having two objects , a lit lamp and an unlit lamp which are swapped
as required will be enough for descriptive purposes.

Don't forget that similar conditions must be set up for each move from
dark to light or vice versa, but moving light to light or dark to dark
can be set up using normal connections.











                                 10


                               COUNTERS


While markers are useful to store information about the status of the
game, counters are far more  versatile.  The  ability  to  store  any
number between 0 and 255 opens immense possibilities,  not  only  for
counting turns and scoring!

Almost anything can be stored in a counter as long as it  is  in  the
form of a number. This includes terms such as  TURN,  ROOM,  RAND  x,
VBNO, NO1 and  NO2,  which  all  return  a  number  when  used  in  a
condition.

Counters can also be used to manipulate numbers,  by  using  them  as
temporary stores, and their contents as the values used in arithmetic
expressions.

 Scoring

This is one of the simplest uses of a counter. Counter 0 is  used  to
hold the score, since this is where GAC looks when asked to print the
score at the end of a game, or when the player is killed.

Imagine you had the following puzzles and scores for solving them  in
your game;

1) Find a key.........20 points
2) Kill a giant.......30 points
3) Cross a river......50 points

To increase the  score  when  the  relevant  puzzle  is  solved,  the
condition which covers solving the puzzle needs to  add  the  correct
number of points to counter 0. All counters are set to  0  initially,
and only  the  'turns'  counters  (126  &  127)  change  without  any
intervention.

So, Counter 0 holds the value 0 at the start. There are three ways to
change the value held in a counter:

1) x CSET n - stores the value 'x' in the counter numbered 'n'.  Thus
to store 25 in counter 0 you would use " 25 CSET 0 "  in  the  action
part of a condition.

2) INCR n - adds one to the number held in counter n.  If  counter  0
held the number 25 from the last  example,  using  "INCR  0"  in  the
action part of a condition would result in counter 0 then storing the
number 26. Using "INCR 0" again would result in counter 0 storing  27
and so on.

3) DECR n - subtracts one from  the  number  held  in  counter  n....
exactly the reverse of "INCR n".

Returning to our 'scoring' using counter 0, this is how to do it:

A) IF ( {the player does something to find a key})  CTR 0 + 20 CSET 0
{ and anything else that happens when the key is found}

The 'scoring' part is "( CTR 0 + 20 ) CSET 0 "



                                  11

Taking the part within the brackets first, "CTR  0"  gets  the  value
currently held in Counter 0, and "+ 20" adds 20 to  that  value.  The
result of the 'sum' in the brackets then REPLACES the original  value
held in counter 0 by the action "CSET 0". This might seem a bit  long
winded: why not simply use "20 CSET 0"? The problem with  doing  that
is that since the result of the calculation in the brackets  replaces
whatever was originally held in counter 0, "20  CSET  0"  would  only
give the correct result if counter  0  happened  to  be  holding  the
number "0". A look at  the  condition  for  killing  the  giant  will
demonstrate why the simpler version is inappropriate!

B) IF ({ player kills giant})  CTR 0 + 30  CSET  0   {and  any  other
actions required}

Again, "CTR 0 + 30" is taking the value of counter 0  and  adding  to
it, but assuming the key has  already  been  found,  counter  0  will
contain not 0 but 20 from condition (A). If we simply used  "30  CSET
0", counter 0 would end up holding only 30, not 50 (20 + 30)!

C) IF ({player crosses river})  CTR 0 + 50 CSET 0  {and other actions
reqired}

Assuming the key has been found and the giant killed, counter 0  will
be holding 50, so "CTR 0 + 50" will be the equivalent of  "50  +  50"
giving a total of 100 to store  in  counter  0.  If  we  assume  that
crossing the river completes the adventure, the score (ie  the  value
of counter 0) will be displayed (if marker 3 which can  disable  this
is reset). The puzzles could have been solved in any order,  but  the
final result will still be 100.

Some games penalise the player for 'saving' a game position.  If  you
want to do this, simply alter the routine for saving to include  "CTR
0 - x CSET 0" where 'x' is the amount of the penalty.

 Turns

The number of turns taken by the player are automatically  stored  in
counters 126 & 127. This can be useful if you  want  to  introduce  a
routine where the player will die of hunger if he  doesn't  find  and
eat food within a certain number  of  turns.  Assume  the  player  is
allowed 20 turns from the  start  to  find  and  eat  the  food.  The
following condition will kill him off after the 20th turn if  he  has
not eaten. Here we will use a marker to 'mark'  that  food  has  been
eaten. Any marker (except  the  reserved  ones) will  do...we'll  use
marker 5.

LOW.. IF ( {player eats   food}  )  SET 5  {  and  any  other  action
      required}

HIGH.. IF ( TURN > 20 and RES? 5 ) {kill player}

In this routine, marker 5 will be reset until  the  player  eats  the
food, when it will cahnge to being set. If marker 5 is set, the  High
Priority condition will be ignored. If marker  5  is  reset  and  the
player has not yet taken 21 turns, the High Priority  condition  will
be ignored. But if the player has not eaten (res? 5), and  more  than
20 turns have been taken, he will be killed. 'TURNS' is used here  as
it is a short way of saying 'counter 126'.


                                 12

If later on in the game you wish the player to have a limited  number
of moves in a desert without drinking, 'TURNS' is not much use, since
you don't know what turn the player will reach the desert in, so have
no idea what turn to kill him off in. To overcome this, we can use  a
marker to check when the player enters the desert, and  use  a  spare
counter as a base for our calculation as follows. ( We'll  assume  10
turns are allowed without water, marker  6  to  say  the  player  has
entered the desert, marker 5 for drinking,  and  counter  5  to  keep
track of turns after entering the desert).


LOCAL...( Instead of a connection to the desert location)
IF ( go into desert ) 10 CSET 5 SET 6 enter desert location}

LOW... IF ( {drink water} ) SET 5 { any other actions}

HIGH... IF ( RES? 5 AND SET? 6) DECR 5 END

HIGH... IF ( CTR 5 = 0 AND SET? 6 ) {kill player off}

In this sequence, as the player  enters  the  desert,  counter  5  is
loaded with the value 10 (turns allowed without water) using "10 CSET
5", and the fact that the player has entered the desert is  noted  by
setting marker 6. The first 'high' condition then subtracts one  from
counter 5 every turn unless marker 5 is  set  (  ie  water  has  been
drunk). If marker 5 is reset, counter 5 will  continue  to  decrease,
until eventually ( after 10 turns) it reaches 0. When  this  happens,
the second 'high' condition kills the player off.


 Money

Sometimes you will want your player to be able to  obtain  and  spend
money, tokens etc. To keep  track  of  the  player's  solvency  (  or
otherwise!) use a counter to store the value of his  holding.  Things
can get tricky if you have more than one value of currency, eg 100p =
£1 so initially stick to a single unit. You will need to be  able  to
reduce the value of the counter when the player  spends  money  (  or
perhaps has it stolen ) and increase the value of the counter  if  he
finds ( or steals ) extra cash. If possible, use a counter  with  the
same number as the object it counts....it  makes  keeping  track  and
de-bugging easier!

Assuming counter 100 will hold the money:

 To get money;
IF ( {player gains money}) CTR 100  +  x  CSET  100  {  and  anything
else}....

 To spend/lose money;
IF ({player spends money}) CTR 100  -  x  CSET  100  {  and  anything
else}...

 To count money;
IF ( {player counts money}) PRIN CTR 100 { with messages to  make  it
read well}..


                                 13

 Time

This can be controlled  by  allocating  a  set  number  of  turns  to
represent a unit of elapsed time. If we assume 60  turns  equals  one
'hour', the following routine will give the player  a  time-check  on
request. ( We'll use counter 10 to store  'minutes'  and  counter  11
'hours ).

HIGH.(A) INCR 10 END

HIGH (B) IF ( CTR 10 = 60 ) INCR 11 0 CSET 10 END

LOW .... IF ({ player asks time}) PRIN  CTR  11  PRIN  CTR  10  {with
suitable messages to make it read well}

Using this, minutes will never be greater than 60, as when counter 10
reaches 60, 1 is added to the hours and counter 10 loaded with  0  to
start counting again. You could improve this  routine  by  adding  an
extra counter ( say counter 12 ) to count days. Just add this:

HIGH (C) IF ( CTR 11 = 24 ) INCR 12 0 CSET 11 END

Also add "PRIN CTR 12" to the low condition to  have  days  displayed
too.

These are just a few examples of the ways counters can  be  used.  In
conjunction with the other commands GAC provides, you  can  build  up
virtually any 'counting' routine you wish..........EXPERIMENT!!


                                  14

                         DIAGNOSTICS SCREEN


This shows the state of markers  and  counters  during  the  game.
They can be called up at any point in the game,  by  pressing  ESC
followed by D, and are useful for finding out why something is not
going quite as expected.
The first table shows markers -

MKR   0  1  2  3  4  5  6  7  8  9  0  1  2  3  4  5  6  7  8  9

0
20
40          1
60
80
100
120
140
160                                       1
180
200
220
240

e.g. Marker 42 has been set and so has 172

Note: Markers start off Reset, except for No.0 and  1,  which  are
      used by the system.

The second table shows the state of the counters at  the  time  of
access.  Note that a counter can only hold a number from 0 to 255.
The GAC counter system works in Modulo 255, therefore if a  number
is raised more than 255, it will wrap around back  to  0  and  up,
whilst the opposite happens if a counter is lowered below 0.
N.B.  This  only applies when a counter is changed by:

        CTR [ counter No. ] + [ No. ] CSET [ counter No. ]

Not when it is changed by the INCR and DECR commands.  With  these
when the number reaches a limit (255 or 0), it  will  stay  as  it
was.

CTR      +0      +1      +2     etc.............

10        0       0       0

20        0       0      254

30        0       0       0

40        0       55      0

50        0       0       0

etc.

e.g.  In the above diagram, counter 22 has a value of  254  whilst
      counter 41 has a value of 55.


                                 15

                                 TEXT



STORAGE OF TEXT AND COMPRESSION


As you write your adventure all the words  you  type,  whether  as
messages or nouns for example, are stored in a  dictionary.   Each
new word takes up a number of bytes equal  to  its  length,   plus
another three for a pointer showing its position in memory.  When,
(and if), the word is deleted, part of the pointer remains so that
if you constantly enter and delete words, you would gradually  run
out of memory. The old words remain in memory, the program  merely
ignores them.

When a word is entered that has already been used,  the  GAC  will
refer to its pointer, thus only using up three bytes.
Points to remember are:

a)  Spelling mistakes and typing errors are all stored in  memory,
    so check a line before entering it.
b)  If you are running low on memory, try  using  words  that  you
    have used before.
c)  Words, messages etc are stored in  memory  in  the  order  you
    enter them, which is  why  when  you  do  a  printer  listing,
    (except for the Commodore), local conditions and messages  may
    not be in numerical order.


NOUNS AND VERBS


When entering nouns,  verbs  and  adverbs,  try  to  use  as  many
synonyms as possible, but be  careful  of  overuse,  for  example,
"SCRUTINISE" for "EXAMINE".
With an object such as  "A  CREDIT  CARD",  the  associated  nouns
should be "CREDIT" and "CARD".
It is a good idea to feature "THEM" as noun 255 as well  as  "IT",
if you have objects such as "a pair of shoes".   "HIM"  and  "HER"
can also be included if other  people  feature  strongly  in  your
adventure, (although the  program  will  not  distinguish  between
them!).

The  GAC  handles  abbreviations  automatically,  looking  through
verbs, nouns and adverb tables until it meets a word that  matches
up with the players input.  To explain this  more  fully  we  have
included a sample verb table:

20 EAT
 3 EAST
16 EXAMINE
 7 GET
13 GRAPHICS
10 INVENTORY
 9 L
15 LOAD
 9 LOOK

In the adventure with this verb table,  the  player   could   type
"INVENTORY', "INVEN", "INV" or even just "I", because  it  is  the

                                  16

only verb beginning with "I".  To go  EAST,  however,  the  player
must type "EAST" or "EAS" - simply typing "E" or "EA" would  cause
the program to try to "EAT", due to the fact EAT  is  before  EAST
alphabetically.  To make the program  accept  "E"  for  east,  you
would need to enter "3 E".  A similar thing  has  been  done  with
"LOOK" and "LOAD".


DIFFERENT BUT THE SAME


If you have different types of the same object,  for  example,  "A
RED CARD", "A GREEN CARD", etc., there are several ways of telling
the difference.

a)  Colour as Noun

i.e.    Obj 1  =  "a red card"
       Noun 1  =  "RED"
        Obj 2  =  "a green card"
       Noun 2  =  "GREEN"

If you are doing it this way, it is  a  good  idea to have a  noun
"CARD", (separate from the actual cards), and  have  a  line  that
checks to see if the player has just typed "CARD". If this is so,
a message along the lines of "which one?" is printed up.

b) Use of Adverbs

Probably the best method, but it does mean the   player  has  more
typing to do, is:
                    Obj 1  =  "a red card"
                    Obj 2  =  "a green card"
                 Adverb 1  =  "RED"
                 Adverb 2  =  "GREEN"
                 Noun 100  =  "CARD"

So a line would read as follows:

IF ( VERB [TAKE] AND NOUN [CARD] AND  ADVE  [RED]  AND  HERE  [RED
CARD] ) GET [RED CARD] OKAY END.

c) Priority of Objects

The player need only type "GET CARD" and the  program  will  first
check whether the Red Card is there and get it, if it is.  If  not
the program will check for the Green Card and so on.
This method can be used for cases where there are two objects that
represent one object in two different states and that cannot exist
at the same time, for example a lamp and a lit lamp.


                                 17

                         SYSTEM MESSAGES



These are the messages from 239, (238 for BBC computers), onwards.
They are automatically printed up by GAC if the situation  arises.
The messages and situations are as follows:

238  "nothing." (BBC ONLY)    This is printed when a LIST  command
                              and the area listed, (either WITH or
                              a room), is empty of objects.
239  "You are carrying'. "    Should always have a  space  at  the
                              end, or a colon.  The only  one  GAC
                              does not automatically use.
240  "What now ?...."         Printed up after all High Priorities
                              are  carried  out.  WAIT  and   OKAY
                              return  to  this  section   of   the
                              program.
241  "You Can't."             When the players input  contains  at
                              least  one   word   in   the   GAC's
                              dictionary, but  no  conditions  are
                              met by it.
242  "Pardon ?"               None of the input is recognised.
243  "Press a key...."        Printed after EXIT or if the  player
                              answers Yes to Mess 244.
244  "Are you sure ?..."      Printed after  a  QUIT  command  has
                              been executed.
245  "You've already got that" If a GET command is carried out and
                              the player already has the object.
246  "You haven't got that"   If a DROP command is carried out and
                              the object is not carried.
247  "You can't see that"     If a GET command is carried out  and
                              the object is not HERE.
248  "Carrying too much."     If the objects weight  +  weight  of
                              currently  carried  objects  exceeds
                              STRE.
249 "Your score was"          Leave a space at the  end.   If  the
                              player answers Yes to 244 or  if  an
                              Exit is met.
250 " and you took"           Leave a space at each end.   Printed
                              after Mess 249 and CTR 0.  NOTE:  It
                              is a good idea to print the  maximum
                              score possible.
251  "It is dark. You can't see"  Automatically printed up each
                              move, if marker 0 is reset.
252  "I can't find that anywhere" If a BRIN is carried out and the
                              object in question a) doesn't  exist
                              or b) is in room 0.
253  "You can also see"       Needs a space,  colon  etc.  Printed
                              after room descriptions  if  objects
                              are present.
254  "Okay"                   OKAY  prints  this  and  performs  a
                              WAIT.  It can be printed  without  a
                              WAIT by MESS 254.
255 " turns"                  Needs a space at the front.  Printed
                              after Mess 250 and TURNS.


NOTE:   Messages 249, 250 and 255 can be  used for scoring  during
the game, but their wording must be such that they mean "So far in
this adventure" and "In  the  adventure  you  have  just  played".

                                  18

                               GRAPHICS



CARTOON FILMS ON GAC!   (Amstrad, BBC and Commodore only)


Yes, simple animated cartoons are possible on GAC, although  their
uses are limited.
To draw your cartoon, simply draw one frame of  animation,  redraw
over the parts to be moved in Ink 0, then draw on a new frame.
It is best to stick to lines, as filling can slow the process down
and make the "film" seem jerky.  If the line drawing goes too fast
however, a few fills in the background colour,  (0,0),  will  slow
the action down to the speed required.



ADVANCED GRAPHICS - TECHNICAL


Memory Used  (Bytes)


Function        BBC         Amstrad        Spectrum        Commodore


   /             5             5              5                5
   D             3             3              3                3
   R             5             5              5                5
   E             5             5              5                5
   I             1             1              1                1
   S             3             3              3                3
   F             3             3              3                3
   P (m)         3             3              3                3
  AOT            *             *              *                1
 MIRROR          *             *              *                1




HOW TO SAVE MEMORY IN THE GRAPHICS SECTION


a)  Draw a rectangle instead of 4 lines.
b)  To draw an arc, first draw an ellipse,  then redraw  the  part
    you want with lines.  Step back through the picture and delete
    the ellipse.
c)  Fill an area first and then add details instead   of   filling
    around them.  If adding detail to a stippled fill, try to draw
    it in a colour that is not  one  of  the  two  comprising  the
    shade, this makes it much bolder.
d)  Use the step back and forwards facilities to  delete  mistakes
    made, instead of merely drawing over them.


                                  19

                           ADVANCED COMMANDS


LOOK  -  If you  have  a  problem  whereby  EXAMINING  or  OPENING
         something BRINGS an object, it is user friendly to put  a
         LOOK command after the "A-HA, FOUND  SOMETHING"  message,
         so that the player can see  what  thay  have  found.   Of
         course if you have a  message  that  reads  "YOU  FIND  A
         FROG", for example, this is not necessary.
DESC  -  A neat  use  of  DESC  is  to  have  illustrated  Examine
         messages.  The way to do this is to have a  room  instead
         of a message, with the Examine reply in it, i.e. "It is a
         large, rusty key".  Thus if you have a room, you can also
         have a picture of the object.  The conditional  line  for
         Examine would read something like:

         IF ( NO1 is  within  examinable  object  range  AND  VERB
         EXAMINE ) DESC NO1 WAIT END.

         If you examine object 1, (with Noun 1 presumably), room 1
         will be displayed.  If room 1 is part of your  adventure,
         start all Examine rooms at 200 for example and  DESC  NO1
         + 199.
x SWAP n If two objects are to be swapped  whilst  being  carried,
         they must be of the same weight,  or  problems  with  the
         inventory limit will occur.  If they  are  not  the  same
         weight, simply drop them first.
OBJ n  - This can be used to 'spice up' messages, for example:
         "A rat steals" OBJ n.
         Note that as most objects are "A  gun"  or  "SOME  seed",
         clever wording must be used to avoid "you can't  see  the
         a gun".
LIST  -  List can be used to do backpacks, chests, other  people's
         inventories and so on.   A room must be assigned  to  the
         backpack, for example, as  well  as  the  actual  object.
         Objects placed in the backpack are  sent  to  this  room.
         When the player EXAMINES  or  LOOKS  into  the  backpack,
         print a message "very roomy. It  contains:   "  and  LIST
         [Backpack room].
         It makes the game look neater,  if  after  LIST,  another
         room or "WITH", you have a message  "."   printed at  the
         end.
x to n - If moving an object that the  player  is  carrying,  make
         sure it is DROPPED first or problems with  the  inventory
         will occur as with SWAP.

CTRx + CSETx - Ctr 0 holds your score.  Ctrs 126 and 127 hold  the
               turns and should be left well alone.

CONN  -  This can be used to do a "You can't go that way" routine.
         IF CONN x = 0, it means you cannot go VERB x, so a line :

         IF ( CONN [x] = 0 AND VERB x ) MESS "BLOCKED" WAIT END.

         is required.  This is  more  user  friendly  than  merely
         repeating "You can't".
STRE  -  This can be altered in the course  of  the  adventure  by
         potions of healing and so on.
BRIN  -  Brin x uses 1 less byte than x TO n, so  if  you  have  a
         situation where a new object is brought  to  the  players

                                  20

         location, for example,  a  vending  machine,  it  may  be
         better to use BRIN x if this situation occurs frequently.
         NOTE: objects cannot be brought from room 0, so use  some
         other room such as 500 as an  "object  sanctuary",  where
         all uncreated and destroyed objects reside.
MESS  -  Several can be strung together,  i.e.  built  up  from  a
         stock of short multiple use message.


DEBUGGING NOTE: If debugging your adventure, make up  a  verb  and
put it in the verb table, i.e. 254 x. Then put the following  line
in low priorities:

            IF ( VERB 254 ) BRIN NO1 GET NO1 OKAY END.

This will not work if your uncreated objects start in room 0.   To
use the line, begin at the room you  wish  to  test  and  type  "x
object".


FIND  -  This can be used for 'teleports',  where  the  player  is
         returned to an object either static, (although GOTO would
         work for that), or movable.
WAIT  -  WAIT returns to players input, so if  a  line  containing
         WAIT is true, any following lines will be ignored.

OKAY     Basically MESS 254 WAIT.

PRIN  -  Useful for printing CTR values for  coins,  stamina  etc.
         Can also be used in debugging by using PRIN ROOM.
HOLD  -  By having a value such as  HOLD  65000,  a  press  a  key
         situation can be achieved, as HOLD is stopped when a  key
         is pressed.
GET/DROP These check automatically for the conditions  needed  for
         GET,  for  example,  is  it  here?/are  you  carrying  it
         already?. They are also the only commands that alter  the
         value of your inventory limit, so if you move  an  object
         directly to 0 without dropping it first, its weight  will
         still be in your inventory.


Condition lines do not exist with  'gaps'  between  line  numbers.
For example, if you have lines 1, 2, 3, and type in a line 10,  it
will be moved down to become line 4.
New lines can be inserted between existing lines as  long  as  END
is put at the end. For example:

Line #10 is
                 IF ( VERB 10 ) GOTO 1 WAIT END

If we wanted to enter a line between 10 and 11,  we  could  either
place it at the end of line 10:

    IF ( VERB 10 ) MESS 1 WAIT END if verb 11 mess 15 wait end.

Or before line 11:

     If verb 11 mess is wait end IF ( VERB 50 ) GOTO 2 WAIT END.

In either  case our new line would before 11, 11 and all following
lines would be shunted up 1.

                                  21

The GAC will check through all lines of conditions until it  finds
one that is true.  It will then carry out all actions in the line.
If it encounters WAIT, it will return to  the  input  routine  and
ignore any following conditions.
OKAY is the same as WAIT, except that it  prints  up  message  254
first, so OKAY WAIT END is superfluous.

Use of WAIT can mean that you do not need to check a marker twice.
For Example: Local Condition Room 1

Line 1.....
           IF ( RES? 10 [TROLL  ALIVE]  AND  VERB  KILL  AND  NOUN
          TROLL ) TROLL TO 0 MESS "YOU KILL TROLL" SET 10 WAIT END
Line 2.....
           IF ( VERB KILL AND NOUN TROLL  )  MESS  "ALREADY  DEAD"
           WAIT END

In line 2 marker 10 is not checked because it has to  be   set  if
"KILL TROLL" has been typed and this line is being checked by GAC.
If 10 was reset and "Kill  Troll"  was  typed,  line  1  would  be
carried out, the wait in it would return the GAC to input mode and
line 2  would  never  be  reached.  This  works  best  with  local
conditions.
NOTE that line 2 has a wait on it as well.  This is because  local
conditions are checked before  low and there  is  a  line  in  low
conditions that is:

  IF ( VERB KILL ) MESS "VIOLENCE WILL NOT HELP YOU HERE" WAIT END

This will be printed up if the  player  tries  to  kill  something
other than the troll.
If line 2 did not have the wait, it  would  print  "already  dead.
Violence will not help you here".  This actually makes sense!  But
imagine a hermit who you give an apple,  and  an  error  trap  for
give with no one there, it would come up with;  "Thank'ee  kindly.
No one wants that".

If a line takes up 255 characters without  brackets,  when  it  is
entered the GAC will include brackets and spacing which will cause
the line to be more than 255  characters  long,  which  may  cause
undesirable effects.

                                  22

                   ADVANCED USE OF CONDITIONS



NOUN, VERB, ADVE


It is worth noting that the GAC will understand four words from an
input sentence - 2 nouns, a verb and an adverb.  These of  course,
do not have to be used as nouns, verbs and adverbs. Nouns  can  be
stored under verbs and so forth, for  example,  Noun  1  could  be
"Take", but it is easier to keep to the correct catagories.

HERE


If you have  monsters/obstacles  as  objects,  HERE  can  be  used
instead of a marker. For example, instead of marker 10  being  the
troll - set means dead, 2 objects  can  be  used.  "A  large  ugly
troll" and "a dead troll". Then conditions could be placed in  the
program to control whether the troll is alive or dead.
A line would read:

    IF ( VERB NORTH AND HERE TROLL ) MESS "TROLL BLOCKS PATH"
    WAIT END

followed by;

    IF ( VERB NORTH AND HERE DEAD TROLL ) GOTO NORTH ROOM WAIT
    END

HOWEVER, CARE MUST BE TAKEN - If there is a connection between the
troll room   and  the  NORTH  ROOM,  GAC  will by-pass  the  above
instructions and go directly to the north room, ignoring the  fact
that the troll is there. (See flowchart)

X IN n    (See Errata Information also)


This can be used in a similar  way  to  HERE. For  example,  in  a
shop, all objects for sale can be stored in an inaccessable  room,
say 200.  Instead of having a marker to determine whether an  item
has been purchased, check whether  it  is  in  200  using  200  IN
object. If it is then the player may buy it.
NOTE:  IN must go at the start of a conditional expression.

Set? & Res?


Used to  check  the  state  of  markers.   Markers  are  used  for
something that has two possible forms, for example, a  chest  open
or closed/whether a button has been pressed etc.  Physical objects
such as doors, chests, monsters and so on, can be done using HERE,
but markers are useful for things such as determining whether  you
have  initiated  the  self  destruct  sequence  or  are  under  an
invisibility spell.
NOTE: Remember the ? on the Set? !!

                                  23

Some built in markers are:

Mkr 0 -  If set, it means a room has  been  described  since  last
         reset, (either by moving,  looking  or  DESC).   This  is
         useful for high priorities relating to the colour of  the
         sky for instance.  A RESE 0 command must be placed  after
         all checks for SET? 0 in high priorities.
Mkr 1 -  If set means room is light.  If reset means room is dark,
         (i.e. print mess 251).  To do this, have local conditions
         when moving from Dark to Light/Light to Dark, (i.e.  from
         the outside to the inside of a cave), which set or  reset
         1 depending on the direction of movement, current  status
         of mkr 1, (so as not to get stack empty), and  any  light
         source available.
Mkr 2 -  If set  means  you  are  carrying  a  light  source,  for
         instance a torch.  Note that  Carr  Torch  has  the  same
         effect as Set? 2.
Mkr 6 -  If reset means it is the first move.  It can be  used  to
         set, sire, print "thanks to GAC" etc.
         For example:  IF ( Res? 6 ) MESS  WELCOME  TO  ***  QUEST
         STRE 100 SET 6 END.
         Effectively any marker can be used for 2 & 6.


CTR


These are used in a similar way to markers, but  for  things  that
have  several  possible  values,  for  example,  money.    Further
information can be found under INCR, DECR, CSET and x EQU? n.

x EQU? n


Does ctr n EQUAL x?  This condition must go  at the beginning of a
set of conditions.

VBNO, NO1, NO2


VBNO = 1 is the same as VERB 1. These conditions return the  value
of the verb/noun etc. and can be used to check whether the  player
has tried to take a  movable  object  or  an  obstacle,  i.e.  all
takeable objects have nouns below 50.

          IF ( NO1 < 50 AND VERB TAKE ) GET NO1 OKAY END.

If VBNO, NO1 or NO2 = 0, it means that the  player  has  typed  in
something that is not in the games vocabularly.   This  means  you
can do lines such as:

   IF ( VBNO = 0 ) MESS "I DON'T KNOW HOW TO DO THAT" WAIT END.

ALGEBRA


Any condition containing <, >, +, -, must go at the FRONT of a set
of conditions. This also applies to RAND and IN. For example:

               IF ( VERB 7 AND NO1 > 8 ) MESS 1 END

                                  24

will not work properly, whereas

               IF ( NO1 > 8 AND VERB 7 ) MESS 1 END
is correct.
Because  EQU?,  IN  and  ALGEBRA  must  go  at  the  beginning  of
conditional lines, if you wish to check two of them, for  example,
IF NO1 < 8 and 5 EQU? 7, you must use two lines and a marker:

                    1 IF ( NO1 < 8 ) SET 40 END

             2 IF ( 5 EQU? 7 AND SET? 40 ) MESS 1 END

High priority line 1 must be RESE 40, otherwise line 2 will happen
without line 1 being  true.   The  way  these  lines  work  is  as
follows:

1 IF NOUN was less than 8, SET 40

2 IF Ctr 7 = 5 and 40 is SET (line 1 must have been true therefore
NOUN less than 8 ) MESS 1 END.

If you remember that Room, VBNO, N01, NO2, TURN, WEIG and CTR  (X)
are all numbers disguised as words, you can carry  out  sums  with
them, set Ctrs to them, GOTO them and all sorts of things.


                                  25

               MULTIPLE LOADING TECHNIQUES



There are several ways in which  to  implement  multiple
loading techniques.

The first is to simply have each part as a  stand  alone
adventure, for example, "EUREKA".

The second is the password  method,  whereby  completing
one part gives you the password for the next.   A  point
to note is that if this method is used, a word the  same
as the  password,  minus  one  letter,  eg.  PASSWORD  &
PASSWOR must be defined to ensure the whole password  is
typed.

The final method is the load/save method.  This  entails
saving a status out at the end of one part  and  loading
it in at the beginning of the next.
SAVE command saves  out  status  of  markers,  counters,
objects, relevant nouns and your current  room,  so  ALL
these must match for all parts.
It is a good idea to set a marker at the end of one part
and check for it in the next part to ensure it is a save
from a completed game.


                                  26


                           ERROR MESSAGES   (Additional)



ROOM NOT FOUND       The program has been sent to a room that  has
                     not been defined, (either by beginning there,
                     by use of GOTO or by an exit)

MESSAGE NOT FOUND    The  program  has  been  told  to  print   an
                     undefined message.   Use  the  line  that  is
                     printed up to determine which.  If  the  line
                     contains no undefined message, not found is a
                     system message, (239-255, 238 for BBC  -  See
                     System Messages).

STACK EMPTY          Usually because a "?" is left out or a  space
                     left between the SET or RES conditions.


ILLEGAL VALUE         A value that is either  negative  or  exceeds
                      the maximum value. (See Appendix A - Amstrad,
                      Appendix B(v) - BBC, Commodore, Spectrum  for
                      the  range  of  numbers  for  maximum  values
                      possible).   It  will  usually  be  a  number
                      greater than 255 that is causing the trouble.



                                  27

                        ERRATA INFORMATION



Advinman messages  (Chapter 5 - Amstrad, App.A - Others)


1.  It is a small battery operated lamp.

2.  It is a freshly dead rat.  Looks tasty!

3.  It is a small silver key.

4.  It looks valuable.

5.  It is a small lamp, shining brightly.

6.  You can't walk through doors you know!

8.  The snake wakes up, comes over  and  bites  you.   The  poison
    takes hold immediately.

9.  Well done!  You got out with the gold.  You are rich!

10. The door unlocks and swings open.

13. The snake wakes up, comes over and  eats  the  rat.   It  then
    returns to its position.

14. The snake, not surprisingly takes a nasty turn and bites  you.
    The venom kills you.

15. It lights up brightly.

16. It goes out.

17. It tastes even better than it looks!  Yum Yum!

18. You find nothing much.

19. I'm afraid I don't know what that is.

20. You hear scuffling footsteps nearby....

21. A giant spider with glowing red eyes leaps  from  the  shadows
    and  neatly  severs  your  head  with  powerful  jaws,  before
    devouring you.


Conditions

Amstrad

x IN n     Is object n in room x?  If object 1 is in  room  3,  as
           above, then 3 IN 1 will be true, but 4  IN  1  will  be
           false.
Others

r IN 0     Is object 0 in room r?  If object 1 is in  room  3,  as
           above, then 3 IN 1 will br true, but 4  IN  1  will  be
           false.


                                  28

    QS verbs   (All except Amstrad)


    For 12 EXITS, read 12 TEXT.




    KEY - A = Amstrad
          B = BBC
          C = C64
          S = Spectrum



    Appendix B - Words Used In Conditions, Objects

      (iii) BBC + Spectrum/(iv) C64

BCS   For o in r, read r in o


    Appendix A - Table iii - Conditions High Priority

BCS  For Res  ?  read Res?
     For Equ  ?  read Equ?


    Verbs - 2.2

BS  Para.3, line 1  should read:

    "To enter a verb, simply type in a number then a space followed by
    your verb".


    Graphics - 3.2

S   G - Displays Attribute grill.   Must be held down.


A   Section 2

    You may have as many connections from a single room as you can fit
    into 255 characters, all on a single line and followed by  RETURN.
    For example:  EAST 20 WEST 18 NORTH 19 SOUTH 21 jump 49  (RETURN).


    Appendices A & B

S   Where it reads "Tape or Disc", ignore "or Disc".


                                  29

                       AMSTRAD HINTS AND TIPS


Control Characters

The Control Characters explained in Chapter 9 of your User  Manual
can be incorporated into your GAC programs to produce  effects  on
screen and in game.
Control Characters can be entered as  rooms  or   messages   using
the following notation:

                   [CTRL + KEY], <PARAMETERS>.

Some useful control characters to remember are:

SET PEN NO.
[CTRL] + 10] n            (n is the pen number [0-3])

SET PAPER NO.
[CTRL] + [N] n            (n is the paper number [0-3])

Clear screen.

[CTRL] + [L]

Move cursor

[CTRL] + [J]              Down one line  (LF)

[CTRL] + [K]              Up 1 line

[CTRL] + [H]              Left 1 character

[CTRL] + [I]              Right 1 character (space)

Inverse Video on/off

[CTRL] + [X]              Toggles inverse video on or off

Beep

[CTRL] + [G]              Can  be  used  if  something  important
                          happens.
Change pen colour (INK)

[CTRL] + [\] n  xx

n is the pen number (0-3).
x is a letter representing a colour (as in Appendix B of your  GAC
manual).
NOTE: If two different x's are specified, the ink will be flashing
between them.

[CTRL] + [J]  xx          Set border colour

Where x is a letter representing a colour (as above).

Change screen mode.

[CTRL] + [D] n            n is mode number (0-2)

                                  30

This is not advisable with graphics  on  screen!   Note  that  the
Auto-formatter in GAC is set to 40 columns, so in mode 2 only half
the screen will be used.

Other Control Characters can be found in Chapter  9  of  the  User
Manual, but their use in GAC is limited.


Graphics


Due to differing ROM routines for  line  drawing  across  the  CPC
range, your graphics may  differ  on  all  Amstrad  machines.  The
answer is simple - avoid where at all possible  filling  with  the
cursor adjacent to a line, or "fill leakage" may  occur  when  the
game is transferred from 664/6128 to 464 or vice versa.
If you own a 464 without a disc drive and are thinking  of  making
your game commercially available, your game  will  reach  a  wider
audience if you leave 1400 bytes free for the disc drive  inherent
to other CPC's.


Conditions


With some complicated commands, for example: NO1 SWAP ( NO1 + 10 )
the brackets are removed when the line is  entered  and  the  line
cannot be re-edited.  Replace the missing brackets each time,  and
everything will work okay!


                                  31

                         AMSTRAD ERRATA



Advinman Messages    (Chapter 5)

1.  It is a small battery operated lamp.

2.  It is a freshly dead rat.  Looks tasty!

3.  It is a small silver key.

4.  It looks valuable.

5.  It is a small lamp, shining brightly.

6.  You can't walk through doors you know!

8.  The snake wakes up, comes over  and  bites  you.   The  poison
    takes hold immediately.

9.  Well done!  You got out with the gold.  You are rich!

10. The door unlocks and swings open.

13. The snake wakes up, comes over and  eats  the  rat.   It  then
    returns to its position.

14. The snake, not surprisingly takes a nasty turn and bites  you.
    The venom kills you.

15. It lights up brightly.

16. It goes out.

17. It tastes even better than it looks!  Yum Yum!

18. You find nothing much.

19. I'm afraid I don't know what that is.

20. You hear scuffling footsteps nearby.....

21. A giant spider with glowing red eyes leaps  from  the  shadows
    and  neatly  severs  your  head  with  powerful  jaws,  before
    devouring you.


Conditions   (Section 4.i)


The command "IN" is documented incorrectly.  The corrected version
is as follows:

"x IN n        Is object n in room x?  If object 1 is in room 3 as
               above then 3 IN 1 will be true, but 4 IN 1 will  be
               false.


                                  32

Section 2


The section on exits should include the following:

"You may have as many connections from a single room  as  you  can
fit into 255 characters, all on a  single  line  and  followed  by
RETURN, i.e. EAST 20 WEST 18 NORTH 19 SOUTH 21 JUMP 49 (RETURN).


Section 4


The example line should read:

IF ( VERB 9 ) LOOK WAIT END

(Verb 9 = LOOK)


                                  33

    ___________
    |  START  |
    |_________|
         |
         |---------------<-------
_________V________
|     output     |
|ROOM DESCRIPTION|
|________________|
         |
   ______V______
   | TURNS + 1 |
   |___________|
         |
_________V_______
| HIGH PRIORITY |
|  CONDITIONS   |
|_______________|
        |
  ______|_______
 /   output    /
/  MESSAGE 240/
--------+------
 _______|_______
/PLAYER'S INPUT/
---------------










         The internal commands QUIT and EXIT return the player to the first
         room with the program initialized.    There is no end as such.

                                  34

                        BBC HINTS AND TIPS



Message + Goto

When in graphics mode (PICT),  the  GAC  clears  the  screen  when
moving from location to location, so if you wish to have a MESSage
followed by a GOTO, you will need to have HOLD command of suitable
length between the two.

Reset start

When a datafile is loaded into GAC, the Begin Where? value is not,
you will therefore either have to begin your adventures in Room 1,
(default), or remember to change the  Begin  Where?  value  before
saving each time.

Border

The border around the Graphics area,  whilst  using  the  Graphics
Editor will not be present in your  runnable  adventure.   If  you
wish to have one, simply draw a rectangle encompassing the  entire
screen area.
Because GAC uses interrupts to produce two modes at the same time,
the bottom two pixels may become corrupt.  To prevent this, draw a
border as above but move it up two pixels from the bottom.

Bug

Sometimes an error may occur with the  formatter  where  the  game
will print a location description and then  lock-up.   To  prevent
this simply alter the length of the offending room description  by
adding or changing one or two words.

Memory free

There is approximately  18K  free  for  use  in  your  adventures.
However a certain amount of memory must be assigned to each  part,
Graphics and Text.
There must be at least 2K used on Graphics  and  at  least  3K  on
Text. As the memory is depleted on the GAC Main  Menu,  a  message
"available for graphics" will appear, showing how much K there  is
left for your pictures.

Deleting lines from your game

To delete whole condition lines, rooms etc.  Press f0.  Delete  is
only used to change part of a line. i.e.

                    IF ( VERB 9 ) LOOOK WAIT END

If we want to get rid of the extra "O" in  "look",  (so  that  the
line can be entered), move the copy cursor up to the beginning  of
the line, copy out the line until the offending  word  is  reached
and either:
a)  move the copy cursor past it before continuing copying, or
b)  copy it out and use delete to erase the  mistake  or  unwanted
    part.

F0 will erase the whole thing.

                                  35

                            BBC ERRATA



Advman Messages     (Appendix A.v)


1.  It is a small battery operated lamp.

2.  It is a freshly dead rat.  Looks tasty!

3.  It is a small silver key.

4.  It looks valuable.

5.  It is a small lamp, shining brightly.

6.  You can't walk through doors you know!

8.  The snake wakes up, comes over and bites you. The poison takes
    hold immediately.

9.  Well done! You got out with the gold. You are rich!

10. The door unlocks and swings open.

13. The snake wakes up, comes over  and  eats  the  rat.  It  then
    returns to its position.

14. The snake, not surprisingly takes a nasty turn and bites  you.
    The venom kills you.

15. It lights up brightly.

16. It goes out.

17. It tastes even better than it looks! Yum yum!

18. You find nothing much.

19. I'm afraid I don't know what that is.

20. You hear scuffling footsteps nearby.....

21. A giant spider with glowing red eyes leaps  from  the  shadows
    and  neatly  severs  your  head  with  powerful  jaws,  before
    devouring you.


Conditions     (2.7.i)


The command "In" is incorrectly documented.  The  correct  version
is as follows:

"r IN o        Is object 0 in room r? If object 1 is in room 3  as
               above, then 3 IN 1 will be true, but 4 IN I will be
               false.

                                  36

QS Verbs      (Appendix B)


For "12 EXIT" read "12 TEXT".


Appendix B.iii


For "o IN r"  read "r IN o".


Appendix A.iii. Conditions


For "RES ?" read "RES?".
For "EQU ?" read "EQU?".


Verbs (2.2)


Para.3 line 1 should read:

"To enter a verb, simply type in a number then a space followed by
 your verb."


                                  37

                    COMMODORE - SPECIFIC HINTS


Message and goto


When in grpahics mode (PICT),  the  GAC  clears  the  screen  when
moving from location to location, so if you wish to have a message
followed by a GOTO, you will  need  to  have  a  HOLD  command  of
suitable length between the MESS and the GOTO.

Control Characters   (Used in Descriptions and/or Messages)


The Control Characters in Appendix B section ii of the GAC  manual
can be used for various effects.
Their types and effects are given in the manual.  Suggestions  for
their use are:
 i)  To emphasise something - (CTRL G and REVS ON/OFF).
ii)  To change the screen/text colour either to highlight a word ,
     (see above) or to fit the description without a picture,  eg.
     A  lava  flow  description   could   have   red   paper   and
     orange/yellow text.

AOT/Mirror


"Mirror" REFLECTS left onto  right  or  top  onto  bottom.   Using
Mirror you can save work and memory, especially on  borders  where
only the top right hand corner need be  drawn.   After  Mirroring,
other features can be added to prevent the  picture  from  looking
symmetrical, (see the Castle picture in RANSOM).

AOT can be used to produce variety in  similar  pictures,  or  for
views from different angles.
If you wish to mirror right onto left, or bottom onto top, AOT the
screen first.
Slight animation can be achieved by "AOTing" virtually symmetrical
pictures.

Colour Scheme


If you have the programmers reference  guide,  you  may  find  the
table on page 152 of some use when deciding on text colour etc.
If you  haven't,  Black  and  White  are  the  best  colours,  but
experimentation is always the best method.


                                  38

                      COMMODORE ERRATA SHEETS



Advinman messages


1.  It is a small battery operated lamp.

2.  It is a freshly dead rat.  Looks tasty!

3.  It is a small silver key.

4.  It looks valuable.

5.  It is a small lamp, shining brightly.

6.  You can't walk through doors you know!

8.  The snake wakes up, comes over  and  bites  you.   The  poison
    takes hold immediately.

9.  Well done!  You got out with the gold.  You are rich!

10. The door unlocks and swings open.

13. The snake wakes up, comes over and  eats  the  rat.   It  then
    returns to its position.

14. The snake, not surprisingly takes a nasty turn and bites  you.
    The venom kills you.

15. It lights up brightly.

16. It goes out.

17. It tastes even better than it looks!  Yum Yum!

18. You find nothing much.

19. I'm afraid I don't know what that is.

20. You hear scuffling footsteps nearby....

21. A giant spider with glowing red eyes leaps  from  the  shadows
    and  neatly  severs  your  head  with  powerful  jaws,  before
    devouring you.


Conditions   (2.8 i)


The command "IN" is incorrectly documented.  The  correct  version
is:

"r IN o    Is object o in room r?  If object 1 is  in  room  3  as
           above then 3 IN 1 will be true, but  4  IN  1  will  be
           false.


                                  39

QS Verbs (Appendix B)


For "12 EXIT" read "12 TEXT".


Appendix B iv


For o IN r, read r IN o.


Appendix A iii - Conditions


For "Res ?" read "Res?".
For "Equ ?" read "Equ?".


Loading QS and ADVINMAN


To load QS and ADVINMAN, the filenames MUST be typed in CAPITALS
without quotation marks.


                                  40

                       SPECTRUM HINTS AND TIPS



Graphics


Due to the way the Spectrum handles graphics on screen,  only  two
colours can be present per character square...the paper  colour  -
Attribute and the foreground colour - the ink.
Note:  Once something has been drawn on screen in ink, there is no
way of re-drawing over it.
With only two colours per square, you may think there  isn't  much
scope for multi-coloured graphics  in  your  adventure,  but  with
careful positioning of your lines and nodes where lines join, many
colours may be displayed adjacently.


Filled with blue ink



                                        Bank lines


                                        Red (attribute) filled bricks






                                        Bank lines


                                        Filled with ink red


Green (attribute) filled grass


"Bank lines" are to contain the ink Fill (F).      This enables the
area outside the bank line to be attribute filled (A) and detail
drawn on it. For example, in the house picture above, all the
side of the house is filled in red, but the bottom sections are
filled in Ink as the other half of the character squares are
filled in Attribute green. This enables windows and bricks to be
drawn on the rest of the house, and bushes etc to be drawn on the
grass in ink. It is a good idea to fill large areas in attribute
so that detail may be put on to make it less boring.

It is helpful to draw and plan graphics on squared paper first,
and use "G" whilst in graphics mode to bring up the character
grid.
For more information on Bank lines and so on see picture 99 of
Advinman.

Message and Goto


If you have a message followed by a Goto command, the room
description will be printed one line up, obscuring the last line
of the message. The answer is to have a line feed command (LF)
between the MESS and the GOTO.

                                  41

Should your datafile become corrupt use the following method of
retrieving your datafile:

1. Note memory free
2. Turn Spectrum OFF then ON to clear
3. Clear 40000 (Enter)
4. Load in datafile: Load"" Code
5. Poke (65536 - memfree), 0
6. Poke (65537 - memfree), 0
7. Then Save "Datafile" CODE 42271, (23267 - memfree)
8. Reload GAC and load new file


                                  42

                    SPECTRUM ERRATA SHEETS




Advinman messages  (Appendix A v.)


1.  It is a small battery operated lamp.

2.  It is a freshly dead rat.  Looks tasty!

3.  It is a small silver key.

4.  It looks valuable.

5.  It is a small lamp, shining brightly.

6.  You can't walk through doors you know!

8.  The snake wakes up, comes over  and  bites  you.   The  poison
    takes hold immediately.

9. Well done!  You got out with the gold.  You are rich!

10. The door unlocks and swings open.

13. The snake wakes up, comes over and  eats  the  rat.   It  then
    returns to its position.

14. The snake, not surprisingly takes a nasty turn and bites  you.
    The venom kills you.

15. It lights up brightly.

16. It goes out.

17. It tastes even better than it looks!  Yum Yum!

18. You find nothing much.

19. I'm afraid I don't know what that is.

20. You hear scuffling footsteps nearby....

21. A giant spider with glowing red eyes leaps  from  the  shadows
    and  neatly  severs  your  head  with  powerful  jaws,  before
    devouring you.


Conditions (2.7 i)


The command "IN" is incorrectly documented.  The corrected version
is as follows:

"r IN o            Is object o IN romm r? If object 1 is in room
                   3 as above then 3 in 1 will be TRUE, but 4 in 1
                   will be FALSE."


                                  43

QS Verbs  (Appendix B)

For "12 EXIT" read "12 TEXT".


Appendix B iii


For "o IN r" read "r IN o".


Appendix A iii - Conditions


For "Res ?" read "Res?"
For "Equ ?" read "Equ?"


Verbs 2.2


Para.3, line I should read:

"To enter a verb, simply type in a number then a space followed by
 by your verb."


Graphics 3.2


The command "G" should read:

"G -  Displays a grid showing Attribute positions  whilst  key  is
      held down."


Appendices A and B


Where the text reads "Tape or Disc", ignore the "or Disc".


                                  44

  DE-PROTECTING SPECTRUM ADVENTURES ( & ADDING A NEW CHARACTER SET )
  ------------------------------------------------------------------


1. With an empty Spectrum save out a header on a blank tape.
   SAVE "filename" CODE 24000,41536  ( save header only )

2. Position runnable adventure tape after the 2 headers. i.e. just
   before the large block of code.

3. CLEAR 23999 ( enter )

4. LOAD "filename" CODE ( to load in header )

5. Load in program code. Ignore any  tape loading error that may occur
   at the end of the load.

6. You now have your program in memory.

7. LOAD "charset" CODE 38785,736 ( To load in character set - SPACE to
   COPYRIGHT )

8. Save out program. SAVE "name" CODE 24000,41536



To load in your program with the new character set :-

   CLEAR 23999
   LOAD "name" CODE
   POKE 23606,129
   POKE 23607,150
   RANDOMIZE USR 34104



This information has been kindly  provided  by  Simon Kimberley of 115
Yelverton Road, Radford, Coventry. CV6 4AG. A tape is  available  from
Simon containing a minimum of 9  different character sets varying from
old style to ultra modern and  a  font creator with many features. The
price is just 1.49!


                                  45

                    ADVENTURE CLUBS AND MAGAZINES


 ADVENTURE HELP/CLUBS AND MAGAZINES

 When writing please help by enclosing a stamped addressed envelope
 for the reply.

 Adventureline Club (The Guiding Light),
 52 Micawber Way, Newlands Spring,
 Chelmsford, Essex.  CM1 4UG

 The Adventurers Club Ltd.,
 64c Menelik Road, London.  NW2 3RH

 Orcsbane,
 84 Kendal Road, Hillsborough,
 Sheffield. S6 4QH

 Insight,
 41 Union Court, Otley,
 W.Yorkshire.  LS21 3AS

 Adventurers Anonymous,
 Rivendale, Nethergate Street,
 Bungay, Suffolk.  NR3 1HE

 Adventure Probe,
 78 Merton Road, Wigan.  WN3 6AT

 Questline Adventure Help,
 17 Headley Way, Headington,
 Oxford.  OX3 0LR


 ADVENTURE WRITING HELP

 Adventure Contact,
 13 Hollington Way,
 Wigan.  WN3 6LS


 ADVERTISEMENT!

 Incentives Medallion Adventure Label has been set up  specifically
 for the best GAC generated adventures!
 Available now from all leading retailers, or order direct by  Mail
 Order - all programs sent 1st Class post free.

The Legend of Apache Gold- Amstrad, Commodore 64 and Spectrum -
                                                              £7.95
Winter Wonderland- Amstrad, BBC B, Commodore 64 and Spectrum  -
                                                              £7.95

 Also  available  is  a GAC  Adventure  Designer  Pad -  designed
 specifically for orderly information  keeping,  whilst  generating
 adventures, (approx. 200 sheets) -                           £7.95

Incentive Software Limited- 2 Minerva  House  -  Calleva  Park  -
 Aldermaston - Berkshire.  RG7 4QW

                                  46

