King's Valley

In ancient times, when Egypt was at the height of its glory,
great rulers and pharaohs built hidden tombs in a secret place,
deep in the mountains, so that robbers could not find them. As
is known from ancient times to this day, there have been many
insightful robots on earth, many of whom presented themselves
as real archaeologists and all for the sake of countless treasures
and artifacts burdened with the pharaohs and their families.
A total of 64 hidden toms were built, which were carved into
the depths of rocks and cliffs, and the burial site was called
the Valley of the Pharaohs. There, the holiest rulers of Ancient
Egypt hope to remember forever in the races of their glory, even
after death. Alas, their wish did not come true, with the exception
of the tomb of the great Tutankhamun in Thebes. The tombs were
planned and destroyed, leaving simple ruins. However, over time,
many rulers were recalled in other secret places, and some of
their treasures were reserved, including those that kept the
secret of eternal life in the kingdom of the Sun God.

Vic is an English adventurer, originally from Manchester. Known
for his famous fame, he decided to go to the Valley of the Pharaohs
to find treasures and challenge the wisest minds of Ancient Egypt
and their resourcefulness.

Will he be able to solve the riddle of the stone toms?

Will he become another victim of the curse of the mummies?

Will he find the treasures and return home safe?

How to play?

– The game is designed for one person, and the opposite is the
computer.

– Control is carried out using the keyboard or the Sinclair joystick.
– At the beginning of the game you have five lives. However,
for the first 10,000 points and every subsequent 20,000 points,
you will receive an extra life.

– To open the secret doors to the next and previous pyramids,
you need to collect all the jewels in the pyramid.

– If the mummy touches you, you will die.

– To pause or continue the game, press the “H” key.

– The “R” key will help you return to the beginning of the pyramid
if you are “stuck”, but you will lose a life.

Controls

O: left

P: right

Q+O or Q+P: up the stairs

A+O or A+P: down the stairs

M or SPACE: fire

If Vic is not holding anything in his hands, he can jump.

If Vic has a pickaxe, he can chop holes, but after that the pickaxe
is lost.

Tips

You can only go one way through the revolving doors, and mummies
can't go through them. So take note.

When digging a hole, be careful, if it's too deep, you won't
be able to jump out.

You can't dig at the bottom of stairs, at the top and bottom
of revolving doors, under a word, or in places where pickaxes
are left.

Points

Kill a mummy – 100 points

Find a treasure – 500 points

Complete a level – 2000 points