          ===============================================
          |   Manic Mixup: The 2018 Manic Miner Remix   |
          |                                             |
          |  Game Builders: Andy Ford & Ian Rushforth   |
          |                                             |
          |     Technical Development: Ian Rushforth    |
          |                                             |
          |                (jswmm.co.uk)                |
          ===============================================


"Times are tough for poor old Willy. Decades of excessive partying
have taken their toll on his finances. Despite already having downsized
his mansion in 'Jet Set Mini', he is finding it increasingly difficult
to afford the cost of maintaining his home, and keeping his formidable
housekeeper Maria in the style to which she has become accustomed!
And so, after dusting down his trusty hard hat, Miner Willy descends
back into the subterranean realm where he first made his fortune
35 years ago. Emerging into the Central Cavern, he soon notices
that things have changed somewhat since the last time he ventured
down here..."

***********************************

'Manic Mixup' is a remix of Matthew Smith's classic ZX Spectrum
48K game 'Manic Miner', and is released in 2018, 35 years after
the original game. It can be played on a real Spectrum, on the Sinclair
ZX Spectrum Vega/Vega+ or on a computer, games console or another
device using a ZX Spectrum emulator.

The starting point for 'Manic Mixup' was an amalgamation of two
projects by Dr Andrew Broad: his laterally-inverted version of 'Manic
Miner' ('reniM cinaM') and Andrew's 2008 remix of 'Manic Miner'.
Into this melting pot was poured a cluster of newly-designed special
features, making 'Manic Mixup' quite unique amongst games based
on the MM game engine.

Thematically, 'Manic Mixup' is a sequel to the authors' previous
game 'Jet Set Mini', which was a modified version of 'Jet Set Willy'
- that in itself being Matthew Smith's sequel to 'Manic Miner'.
What a mixup!

All of the original caverns (and their perilous occupants) have
had an overhaul in 'Manic Mixup', and the in-game music has been
significantly enhanced. Furthermore, nearly all of the routines
in the 'Manic Miner' game engine have been rewritten or redesigned
for this project, for various reasons: to provide additional functionality
(such as new sound and visual effects, and additional gameplay elements
- including putting Willy's hard hat to good use!); to increase
the efficiency of the code; and to fix various bugs in the original
game engine.

However, the essence of this 8-bit, 48K game will be very familiar
to devotees of 'Manic Miner'. We hope it gives you 'unalloyed pleasure'!
Contents

I. Acknowledgements and thanks

II. Instructions

III. The in-game music

IV. Speed of the game engine

V. Technical notes

VI. The legal bit

VII. Closing remarks


----------------------------------------------------------------------
I. Acknowledgements and thanks

The authors would like to express their gratitude to:

- Matthew Smith, creator of the original 'Manic Miner' and 'Jet
Set Willy'. Some sprites and cell graphics from 'Jet Set Willy'
were used in 'Manic Mixup'.

- Dr Andrew Broad, for the laterally-inverted version of 'Manic
Miner', titled 'reniM cinaM' (from his 'Party Willy' box-set), and
for Andrew's 2008 remix of 'Manic Miner' (released as a bonus with
the JSW64 game engine project 'Flash Manic Miner'). Both of the
aforementioned Broadsoft MM games were blended to form the starting
point for the development of 'Manic Mixup'. Andrew's 2008 MM Remix
was inspired by an interview with Matthew Smith in the Load 48 issue
of 'Retro Gamer' magazine (published in February 2008), and that
interview also provided a source of inspiration for the further
evolution of Matthew's original game into 'Manic Mixup'. Thanks
also to Andrew Broad for his published technical documents (http://www.oocities.org/andrewbroad/spectrum/willy/),
particularly his 'Manic Miner Room-Format', and for establishing
and managing the Manic Miner & Jet Set Willy Yahoo! Group (https://groups.yahoo.com/neo/groups/manicminerandjetsetwilly/info).
- Norman Sword, a regular contributor at jswmm.co.uk, for various
pieces of code which were used or adapted for 'Manic Mixup': in
particular his work on implementing the 'headbutt' feature (a concept
originally conceived by Ian Rushforth); the 'sapping' sound effect
which occurs when Willy is hit by a solar beam (Ian later added
the unique border effect, which causes the border to fluctuate randomly
through all the colours of the Spectrum); Norman's efficient rewrite
of the routine which moves Willy sideways (so that common code is
now used for both left and right movement); a similar efficiency
to handle the animation of conveyors leftwards/rightwards using
common code; Norman's work on fixing the 'Jagged Finger' and 'Delayed
Attribute' visual flaws in the original MM game engine; and his
method for speeding up the game engine, by replacing the original
LDIR method of copying the screen buffers with a subroutine containing
a sequence of 32 consecutive LDI instructions, which is called once
for each time that a raster line/character row is copied.

- John Elliott, for his excellent JSW Editor (JSWED, http://www.seasip.info/Jsw/jswed.html),
which was the main tool used to create the game, and for JSWED's
accompanying documentation.

- Richard Hallas, for his document 'A Miner Triad' (http://hallas.net/Software/music.htm),
a guide to creating music for MM/JSW games which was extremely useful
- especially the tone chart which assigns a byte value (in decimal
and hexadecimal) corresponding to the pitch of each note. Thanks
also to Richard for providing valuable feedback on the in-game,
portal and 'Game Over' tunes in 'Manic Mixup', and for proofreading
the Music section of this Readme file and giving some insightful
suggestions regarding musical terminology.

- Richard Dymond ('SkoolKid'), for his complete Manic Miner disassembly
(http://skoolkid.github.io/manicminer/), which was instrumental
to the implementation of numerous code modifications and optimisations
in 'Manic Mixup'.

- Daniel Gromann, for carrying out extensive playtesting of 'Manic
Mixup' prior to the release of the game, making suggestions for
some of the new cavern names, and for providing useful feedback
on the project. Daniel's JSW Central website (www.jswcentral.org)
is a rich source of information on MM & JSW games.

- Stuart Brady for his Cell-Graphics Bug Fix for the 'Manic Miner'
game engine.

- Jonathan Graham Harston, for his 'Full Z80 Opcode List Including
Undocumented Opcodes' (http://www.z80.info/z80oplist.txt).

- James Moxham, for his 'ZINT Z80 Interpreter' (http://www.z80.info/z80code.htm),
which is a highly informative introduction to the Z80 instruction
set.

- John F. Cain, for his 'Booty' sprite from the game of the same
name.

- Steve Marsden and David Cooke, for a few sprites from their game
'Technician Ted' (some of which are used here in a slightly modified
form).

- K. Maddocks, for the '20 Character Set Fonts' utility (also known
as 'Character Set Collection', Sigmasoft, 1985), from which the
character font used in 'Manic Mixup' was sourced.

- The ZX Spin team, for their ZX Spin emulator (http://www.zophar.net/sinclair/zx-spin.html),
which was used by Daniel Gromann in playtesting.

- Jan Bobrowski, for his Qaop/JS HTML5 ZX Spectrum emulator (http://torinak.com/qaop),
which was used by Ian Rushforth in playtesting.

- Claus Jahn, for his ZX-Modules (http://www.zx-modules.de), particularly
ZX-Paintbrush, ZX-Blockeditor and ZX-Editor which were used by Andy
Ford during the creation of the loading and title screens.

- The authors of Binary Hex Converter (http://www.binaryhexconverter.com/)
which was the standard tool used to convert values back and forth
between the decimal, binary and hexadecimal systems. The Bitwise
Calculator at http://www.miniwebtool.com/bitwise-calculator/ was
also a useful tool.


----------------------------------------------------------------------
II. Instructions

The objective of the game is to guide Willy through a range of subterranean
caverns, collecting all of the flashing items within each cavern,
and then making his way to the exit 'portal' before the air supply
in the cavern runs out. Willy must avoid contact with the moving
guardians and the stationary nasties which will kill him (as will
falling from an excessive height).

There are twenty caverns in the game, but each one has two variants:
an Easy and a Hard version. Once Willy has made his way through
all twenty caverns the first time around - in Easy Mode - a subroutine
is called which edits various parts of the game code (64 addresses
in total), in order to increase the difficulty level throughout
the game. The program then remains in Hard Mode through subsequent
sets of caverns, until the current game comes to an end (at which
point the routine which draws the title screen calls up the same
subroutine, with a different entry point, to edit the 64 addresses
back to their original values, thus restoring the difficulty level
back to Easy before the start of a new game).

So in order to be able to say that you have completed 'Manic Mixup',
you need to work your way through all twenty caverns TWICE during
the course of the same game, completing both Easy and Hard versions
of each cavern!

Keyboard controls:
Use O-Left, P-Right (or a combination of keys from the top row of
letters) and SPACE or any of the letters from the bottom row to
jump.
A-G pauses the game; any other key unpauses it.
H-ENTER/RETURN toggle the music ON/OFF.
Pressing SHIFT+SPACE together at the same time abandons the current
game.

Unlike in the original 'Manic Miner', extra lives are not awarded
for each 10000 points accrued. Instead, Willy is allocated a variable
number of lives for each cavern (commensurate with the difficulty
level of the cavern), which is specified by using a spare 'offset
byte' in the cavern definitions.

The Cheat Mode which allows Miner Willy to teleport between caverns
is still present, but the sequence of keypresses which must be entered
to activate the Cheat Mode has been reversed from the familiar '6031769',
so that it is now '9671306'.

Furthermore, there is a penalty for using the teleport feature -
after using it, Willy will be left with NO spare lives in the destination
cavern (regardless of which cavern it is), although if the player
manages to complete that cavern and reach the next one, then normal
service will resume (i.e. with a number of spare lives allocated
according to the degree of difficulty of the cavern).

Note that playing in Cheat Mode does NOT prevent the transition
from the Easy to the Hard caverns, once Willy has passed through
the 'Final Barrier' cavern the first time around. So if you want
to 'fast forward' to the Hard set of caverns, you may simply teleport
into the 'Final Barrier' (teleport code 1256 as per usual, and it's
a relatively simple cavern 'by tradition'), and then complete it!
'Manic Mixup' has been fully playtested and it is possible to complete
the game without losing a single life.


----------------------------------------------------------------------
III. The in-game music

The original 'Manic Miner' game had, as its theme tune during gameplay,
a rather crude rendition of Edvard Grieg's 1875 composition 'In
the Hall of the Mountain King', consisting of 64 notes played in
a loop.

The in-game tune in 'Manic Mixup' is an attempt at a much more faithful
rendition of 'In the Hall of the Mountain King'. (Dr Andrew Broad
made an earlier attempt to hone the piece for the 2003 Special Edition
of his game 'Manic Miner 4', but that was effectively limited to
a cycle of 32 notes.)

Grieg's 'In the Hall of the Mountain King' is comprised of two alternating
phrases, repeatedly played on alternating instruments. The tune
is grouped into cycles of six phrases - the first phrase is played
on strings and repeated on a woodwind instrument, then the second
phrase is performed likewise, and then there is a reprise of the
first pair of phrases, with the repetition of this phrase (forming
the sixth and final phrase in the cycle) varying slightly towards
the end in order to bring the cycle to a close with the tonic note
of the piece. The overall pace of the piece increases as it progresses
through several six-phrase cycles towards a finishing flourish.
In order to encapsulate as much of the original composition as possible,
the game engine in 'Manic Mixup' has been edited to allow for a
128 note in-game tune (as opposed to 64 notes in the original game
engine). 192 notes would be required to cover each six-phrase cycle,
and so the tune is truncated somewhat - the first three-and-a-half
phrases of the piece are followed by the latter half of the sixth
phrase of the cycle. (The parts that have been excised are essentially
repetitions of earlier phrases, so this seems to be a reasonable
compromise within the constraints of the system.)

The alternating of instruments in Grieg's original piece (between
string/woodwind) is simulated by shifting the pitch up or down an
octave in between phrases (i.e. every 32 notes).

If Willy's air supply reaches the 'red' zone, the pace of the in-game
tune doubles, the timbre of the tune is altered, and a minor third
gets raised in pitch to a major third. These changes replicate the
increased sense of urgency as 'In the Hall of the Mountain King'
approaches its finale, and they serve as a warning to the player
that air/time is running out in the cavern!

Once Willy enters the portal after completing a cavern, there is
an additional 16-note 'celebratory coda', which has been implemented
by tapping into Matthew Smith's original code that causes the screen
to cycle through every permutation of PAPER and INK colour upon
completion of a cavern. This tune represents the finishing flourish
of 'In the Hall of the Mountain King'.

Finally, when Willy has lost all his lives, bringing the current
game to an end, there is a short rendition of an excerpt from Chopin's
Piano Sonata No. 2 in B-flat minor.


----------------------------------------------------------------------
IV. Speed of the game engine

Towards the end of the development of 'Manic Mixup', some changes
to the game engine (credited to Norman Sword) were implemented in
order to speed up the running of the game engine.

However, whilst this improved the overall gameplay, the authors
felt that these changes had a slightly detrimental effect on the
character of the newly-enhanced in-game music. Regular jswmm.co.uk
contributor Daniel Gromann put it best, when he described the in-game
tune as having a "cavernous, haunting quality" when played through
the slower game engine, but that this was diminished when using
the faster engine.

As a result of these deliberations, it was decided to give the player
the option of choosing between a 'Slow' or a 'Fast' game engine.
The speed selection is made during the loading process, with the
options displayed on the loading screen and a keypress ('S' or 'F')
being detected by the BASIC loader. The game engine speed is then
implemented by the loader and is subsequently fixed for the duration
of play (unless the game file is reloaded from scratch).


----------------------------------------------------------------------
V. Technical notes

Most of the routines in 'Manic Mixup' have been rewritten or redesigned
to some extent, in order to provide enhanced functionality, optimise
the code, and fix various bugs and imperfections that were present
in the original 'Manic Miner' game engine.

However, as a general rule, the entry points to the rewritten routines
have been retained at their original locations in the code. For
instance, all of the pre-existing routines CALLed from the game's
Main Loop are located at their original addresses (although they
are not necessarily called up in the same order - for example, the
collectable items in a cavern are now drawn after the portal, rather
than before). This 'familiar' arrangement of the game engine is
designed to ensure that, if you have a good disassembly of the original
MM game engine (such as Skoolkid's) to hand, then you should find
it relatively easy to navigate your way through the 'Manic Mixup'
code.

A notable exception to the above rule is that the routine which
draws the title screen, which is executed as soon as the game is
loaded, commences a single byte later at #85CD instead of at #85CC.
This change was necessary in order to fit a 65-byte subroutine which
is used to implement the 'Fast' game engine (comprised of 32 x 2-byte
LDI operations followed by a RETurn command), into the space where
Matthew Smith's original (now-defunct) 64-byte in-game tune used
to sit (#858C to #85CB).

The new, improved and extended rendition of 'In the Hall of the
Mountain King' is now located at addresses #9C80 to #9CFF, and at
#9B50 to #9B5F. Other significant examples of relocated data are
the 'Skylab' sprite, which is now hardwired into page #94 of the
code, and the 'Booty' graphic, which assumes the former role of
the 'Kong Beast' and which occupies addresses #9B80 to #9BBF. (These
changes permit an independent eight-frame horizontal guardian to
be present in the 'Skylab' cavern, and a four-frame vertical guardian
in the 'Kong' caverns, respectively.) The new tune which accompanies
the 'Game Over' sequence is located at #9BC0 to #9BF0.

It is worth mentioning that the entirety of the huge chunk of unused
addresses in the original MM game engine at #934C to #9CFF inclusive
(occupied in the original 'Manic Miner' game code by source code
remnants) has been recycled for more useful purposes in 'Manic Mixup'.
It should also be noted that in 'Manic Miner' the end of that same
chunk of unused addresses was allocated as the base of the program's
stack. However, in 'Manic Mixup' the stack pointer is diverted to
the end of the unused page #5B of the code (the page of code designated
as the ZX Spectrum's printer buffer, and which is utilised as the
stack by the JSW game engine).

The cavern layout data in the original 'Manic Miner' caverns are
not arranged as efficiently as they could be. For instance, each
collectable item is defined using five bytes, of which one is always
unused. By redefining the items in 'Manic Mixup' more efficiently,
using four bytes per item, it is now possible to insert up to six
items into each cavern (the maximum limit in 'Manic Miner' was five
items per cavern). A side-effect of this change is that the JSWED
editor doesn't recognise the new item definitions, and so the items
don't display properly in JSWED's Graphical User Interface during
editing (items must therefore be inserted into each cavern manually
via the Hex Editor).

Within the original 'Manic Miner' cavern data, there was a repetition
of an entire page (256 bytes) of the code to define identical guardian
graphics for both 'Kong' caverns. This inefficiency has been resolved
in 'Manic Mixup' by making an intervention in the 'Cavern set-up'
routine, whenever Willy enters the second 'Kong' cavern, in order
to copy the guardian graphics from the first 'Kong' cavern's data
into the cavern buffer (i.e. from page #CF to page #81).

That in turn freed up the entirety of page #DF of the code, which
was subsequently utilised as a look-up table for the subroutine
that implements the Easy Mode/Hard Mode regime (as described in
the 'Instructions' section of this Readme file). The look-up table
is populated by 64 entries consisting of four bytes each: a single
byte value for Easy Mode, another byte for Hard Mode, and a two-byte
word specifying the address to be POKEd by one of those two values
at the appropriate time. The subroutine itself which looks up values
from the table is located at #BA90 to #BAAF (with a late entry point
at #BA92 used to revert the game back to Easy Mode).

Other efficiencies in the code that have been implemented in 'Manic
Mixup' include: horizontal guardians are now moved and drawn by
the same routine, instead of by two separate routines individually
called from the Main Loop; common code is used for both leftwards
and rightwards movement of horizontal guardians, for the animation
of conveyors, and for horizontal movement of Willy (Norman Sword's
code to implement the latter two optimisations inspired Ian Rushforth
to devise a similar solution for horizontal guardians); and a shared
subroutine is called up to draw both vertical guardians and 'Skylabs'
(with a variable being defined beforehand, so that the sprite-drawing
subroutine copies the pixel-pattern across from the appropriate
page of the code: either the generic guardian sprite buffer at page
#81, or the hardwired 'Skylab' sprite at page #94).

Nearly all known bugs that were present in the original MM game
engine have been fixed in 'Manic Mixup', including:

- The Cell-Graphics Bug has been eliminated. The effects of this
bug cannot be seen in the original 'Manic Miner', but it was present
in the game engine and could manifest itself during cavern editing
(in fact, it occurs in Andrew Broad's laterally-inverted version
of the game, 'reniM cinaM'). During the process of drawing the current
cavern, a cell's bitmap can become corrupted if that cell's colour-attribute
byte matches with a graphic-data byte which precedes it in the cavern
data. The fix for this bug means that any new cell graphics that
have been created are immune from the effects of the bug.

- The initial air supply in a cavern can now be set to ANY value
within the range covered by the air supply bar. (In the original
MM game engine, certain values will cause a visual glitch, or can
even cause the machine to lock up.) The air bar also displays the
precise amount of air supply (in pixels) at the instant that Willy
enters a cavern (whereas in 'Manic Miner', the initial air supply
is 'rounded up' to the nearest full character on the air bar, which
can cause an instantaneous flicker upon the first pass through the
Main Loop).

- There is no momentary flickering of '000000' in the 'Score' and
'High Score' fields on the status bar, when Willy enters a new cavern.
- Willy can no longer jump into/through wall blocks which are supposed
to be solid.

- Crumbly blocks may now contain intermediate blank pixel-rows,
without leaving 'ghosts' (errant infilled pixels within newly-created
air cells) after Willy has stood on them. Crumbly blocks located
in the top two cell-rows will also crumble in the proper manner
(whereas in the original 'Manic Miner', a quirky effect causes blocks
that are located eight rows beneath to crumble instead!).

- In 'Manic Mixup' it is possible to create a cavern without any
conveyor animation at all. (Some caverns in 'Manic Miner' rely upon
a 'hidden' animation embedded in a non-conveyor cell, in order to
prevent the screen corruption that would otherwise occur in a cavern
where the conveyor length is defined as zero). A further amendment
to the relevant routine allows the additional functionality that
the depth of the lower moving pixel-row within a conveyor block
can be varied.

- A horizontal guardian can now straddle three cell-rows on the
screen, and both its pixel pattern and colour attribute will be
drawn across all three rows. (In the original game engine, the third
cell-row down in such circumstances is updated with the horizontal
guardian's pixels, but not its colour.)

- At times when a guardian is cell-aligned, its colour attribute
will only be drawn across two cell-rows. (In contrast, in 'Manic
Miner' when a 'Skylab' crashes, its colour 'bleeds over' into the
platform below.)

- A vertical guardian can now pass through a collectable item without
causing a fatal collision. It is also now possible to insert a 'blank'
vertical guardian into the guardian list (by using an attribute
value of #00), without preventing all subsequent guardians in the
list from being moved or drawn.

- When a guardian collides with Willy, the whole of that guardian
(its pixel-pattern and its colour-attribute) is drawn before the
collision is acted upon (rather than just the upper rows of the
guardian's pixels, down to the point of collision).

- It is now possible to have one black 'Kong' cavern and another
'Kong' cavern with a non-black background within the same game,
without a 'shadow' appearing in one of the two caverns (around the
'Kong on its perch') that doesn't conform with the surrounding background
colour.

- The laterally-inverted behaviour of the switches in the 'Kong'
caverns has been properly executed, so that a switch is always flipped
when Willy touches it. (In 'reniM cinaM', Willy has to make contact
with a switch with the top-right part of his sprite; the switch
is NOT flipped if the top-left part of his sprite touches it. That
would make 'Manic Mixup' uncompletable if the proper fix for this
wasn't in place.)

- The opening wall in the 'Kong' caverns may contain intermediate
blank pixel-rows, without leaving a 'ghost' after Willy flicks the
switch that causes the wall to open. (In 'Manic Miner', attempting
to have a blank pixel-row in the middle of an opening wall block
will cause such a 'ghost' to be left in the gap where the wall used
to be; and furthermore the adjacent horizontal guardian - whose
range gets edited at that point to allow it to move through the
gap - will collide with the errant pixels, killing Willy in the
process!)

- The new game engine ensures that a solar beam kills Willy as soon
as the air supply runs out. (In the original 'Manic Miner', the
final character of air supply sometimes gets replenished if Willy
is within the solar beam at the time.)

- An item is properly removed from the screen, if it is collected
immediately before Willy enters the portal. (For instance, if Willy
falls through the portal in the sixteenth cavern and collects the
item located below the portal last; in the original 'Manic Miner'
that item remains printed on the screen, even though it has been
collected and 100 points accrued for it.)

- The lower half of Willy's sprite is properly erased from underneath
the portal in the 'Final Barrier' cavern, after he has entered the
portal. (In 'Manic Miner', Willy's legs can still be seen under
the portal whilst the remaining air supply is being counted down.)
- Some visual imperfections (which can be referred to as 'Jagged
Finger'/'Delayed Attributes' effects) have been diminished. These
flaws are caused by the fact that the copying of the pixel and attribute
buffers to the pixel and attribute display files can instantaneously
fall 'out of sync' with the physical updating of the screen's 'raster'
scan lines and the colour attributes printed across each character
row. As a result, moving sprites can momentarily break up and flicker,
and can partially be rendered in the wrong colour attribute for
a brief but perceptible moment. By changing the sequence in which
elements of the display and attribute buffers are copied across,
these effects can be greatly reduced or eliminated.

- Various 'edge of screen conditions' have been resolved (including
preventing the potential corruption of the layout data for cavern
number 7).

- A hypothetical bug fix: if a Score of one million is accrued,
then the High Score will be registered as 999999 rather than 000000
(although it is extremely unlikely that anyone will ever get that
far!)

- One logical flaw/inefficiency in the original 'Manic Miner' code
that hasn't been fixed here is the fact that, when Willy enters
the Final Barrier, the top half of the cavern gets drawn more than
once. The existing check of the current cavern number at the end
of the cavern-drawing routine, made in order to draw the Final Barrier
differently, is now also used to implement some special effects
upon Willy's entry to other caverns in 'Manic Mixup', so the (originally
slightly illogical) architecture of this routine was left in place
and utilised for other purposes. So the top half of the Final Barrier
is still drawn more than once, but this is a relatively harmless
imperfection; it isn't visible to the player and it doesn't slow
down the execution of the Main Loop.

There are many more additional features implemented that haven't
been listed here - to find out more, you'll just have to play 'Manic
Mixup' for yourself and see them in action! (Or, in some cases,
hear them in action - you'll miss a few tricks if you play with
your machine on mute!)


----------------------------------------------------------------------
VI. The legal bit

'Manic Mixup' is freeware, and all of its innovative elements may
freely be reused in other projects. If you do so, please acknowledge
their authorship.


----------------------------------------------------------------------
VII. Closing remarks

We hope you enjoy playing 'Manic Mixup' as much as we did writing
it! Please also check out its prequel, 'Jet Set Mini', an updated
Special Edition of which is released on the same day as 'Manic Mixup'.
If you have any queries, comments or general feedback, please contact
us on the email address below, or come and visit our Jet Set Willy
& Manic Miner Community at jswmm.co.uk to join in with Willy-based
discussion, game development and fun!


Ian Rushforth & Andy Ford, 26th October 2018
projects@jswmm.co.uk